Alex Bair

🔾 Chapel Hill, NC 🗷 alexbair143@gmail.com 🕜 alex-bair.com 🚺 alex-bair

PROFILE

I'm a full stack software engineer with extensive experience in JavaScript, TypeScript, and Ruby. I leverage my engineering and project management backgrounds to deconstruct complex problems and drive them to resolution. I love learning & using new technologies, applying deep technical knowledge to solve difficult problems, and working on a team to build amazing applications.

EXPERIENCE

Creator, Software Engineer, Willow

2024 - present

Willow (willow-cdc.github.io) ☑ is an open-source framework for creating change data capture pipelines. It reflects database changes to a cache in near real-time.

- Developed framework to simplify change data capture pipeline creation from 9 steps to 4 steps.
- Architected and implemented a RESTful API, facilitating pipeline creation and teardown (Node.js, Express).
- Designed and constructed a custom Kafka connector to transform events from Kafka and send them to a cache (Node.js, KafkaJS, Redis).
- Built user-friendly UI to streamline pipeline management (React, Material UI).
- Resolved Debezium configuration issues preventing multiple pipelines from connecting to the same database (PostgreSQL, Debezium).
- Ensured Willow functions when provided a minimum privileged database user, avoiding the need to provide Willow with superuser privileges.
- Collaborated remotely with an international team of four engineers using daily standups and pair programming (Git, GitHub, Slack).
- Authored comprehensive technical case study (willow-cdc.github.io/case-study ⋈).

Software Engineer, Self-employed

2022 - 2024

Developed freelance and open-source applications including:

- Whirlpool Tool for collecting and debugging webhooks (DO Droplet, Nginx, MongoDB, Express, Socket.io).
- Media Watchlist A media tracking web app (Ruby, Sinatra, PostgreSQL, HTML/CSS).

Project Management Specialist, Merck

2019 - 2022

- Led cross-functional teams on a \$46MM capital project portfolio to increase vaccine supply capacity.
- Fostered a collaborative, friendly environment among team members while achieving business objectives.

Photolithography Process Engineer, Texas Instruments

2017 - 2019

Developed detection/interdiction systems using in-house technologies, reducing material holds by 30%.

SKILLS

Backend

Node.js, Ruby, Golang, PostgreSQL, MongoDB, RESTful APIs, Express, Sinatra, Minitest

Frontend

JavaScript (ES6+), TypeScript, HTML, CSS, React, Jest, Handlebars

Other

Git/GitHub, Docker, Linux, Bash, Apache Kafka, Debezium, Nginx, Object Oriented Programming

EDUCATION

Launch School

Multi-year, mastery-based software engineering curriculum. Read more at launchschool.com/employers 🗷

Rose-Hulman Institute of Technology